A Finding Aid to the Colin de Land Collection, 1968-2008, bulk 1980-2003, in the Archives of American Art AAA.delacoli
Archives of American Art
- Photographic Material, bulk 1980-2003; 1968-2003; Series 1; 12 Linear feet Box 1-12
  - Slides, circa 1980s-2003; 1.3
    - Koln Kunstmarkt, 1991 November (Box 14, Folder 26)
      Includes photos of an art fair in Cologne, with artwork by Mark Dion and unidentified gallerists.
    - Documenta, 1992 June (Box 14, Folder 27)
      Includes photos of Documenta IX, with installation shots from Cady Noland, Towards a Metalanguage of Evil, installation by Zoe Leonard, and other unidentified artwork, with Colin de Land, Peter Fend, Esther Friedman.
    - Cape Cod, Summer 1993 or 1994 (Box 14, Folder 28)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn and Jack Pierson.
    - Stella/Prina Opening, 1994 October 22 (Box 14, Folder 29)
      Includes photos of the opening reception for Frank Stella Drawings 1961-1962 and Stephen Prina Dom-Hotel, Room 101, Cologne, Dom-Hotel, Zimmer 101, Koln at American Fine Arts, with Barbara Morse, Lincoln Tobier, Colin de Land, Friedrich Petzel, Liz Clark, Gavin Brown, [J. Corcoran], Patterson Beckwith, and Esther Friedman.
    - Chateau Marmont, 1994 December (Box 14, Folder 30)
      Includes photos of Gramercy Art Fair at the Chateau Marmont Hotel, Hollywood, California, with Colin de Land, Pat Hearn, Paul Morris, Sam Grubman, Leslie Nolan, Craig Wadlin, John Baldessari, and Jack Pierson.
    - Waters/Welling Opening, 1995 April (Box 14, Folder 31)
      Includes photos taken during the installation of John Waters exhibition My Little Movies and James Welling exhibition The Ugly America. Includes Colin de Land, John Waters, Daniel McDonald, James Welling, and Seth Edenbaum.
    - Cape Cod, Summer 1995 (Box 14, Folder 32)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land, Pat Hearn, [members of the Hearn family?], Jack Pierson, Chi Chi.
    - Zurich, June 1995 (Box 14, Folder 33)
      Includes photos of Christian Philipp Muller, Tom Burr, Cathy Torsney, Mark Dion, Colin de Land, Howard Morse, Barbara Morse. Includes installation with script of Paul Morrisey film Trash (or Andy Warhol’s Trash). Also includes photos related to Platzwechsel exhibition at Kunsthalle Zurich with Christian Philipp Muller, Ursula Biemann, Tom Burr, and Mark Dion.
    - Christian Philipp Muller, News and Gifts, 1995 October (Box 14, Folder 34)
      Includes installation shots of Christian Philipp Muller’s News and Gifts at American Fine Arts.
    - Exhibition Installation, 1996 February (Box 14, Folder 35)
      Includes photos of Craig Wadlin and Daniel McDonald installing a [Moyra Davey?] exhibition at American Fine Arts.
    - Parking Violation Refund, 1996 June (Box 14, Folder 36)
      Includes photos of a check made out to Colin de Land from the bureau of parking violations.
    - Pat Hearn Birthday, 1996 July (Box 14, Folder 37)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn’s birthday celebration at El Rey Del Sol, with Pat Hearn, Colin de Land, Gillian Haratani, Cris Moore, Dennis Balk, David Karlin, Patterson Beckwith, Craig Wadlin, [Alex Bag?], Renee Green, Daniel McDonald.
    - New Years Eve, 1996 December (Box 14, Folder 38)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land, Pat Hearn, Paul Morris, Sam Grubman, Christian Philipp Muller, Dan Graham, Tom Burr at the home of Jeff Preiss and Rebecca Quaytman.
    - Patterson Beckwith, Colin de Land, Cris Moor, 1997 April (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Balk and Balk, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 40)
      Includes portraits of Dennis Balk and unidentified woman. Also includes one photo of Red Ed.
    - Elizabeth Peyton, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 41)
      Includes photos of Elizabeth Peyton and Colin de Land with portrait of Colin de Land painted by Elizabeth Peyton. Also includes photograph of John Waters artwork Drunk.
    - American Fine Arts, 1998 January (Box 14, Folder 42)
      Includes photos of Jack Pierson, Peter Fend, Takahiro Imamura, and Rosalie Knox.
    - Rephotographs, 1998 June (Box 14, Folder 43)
      Includes rephotographed photo of Monique Van Vooren, Jocelyn Wildenstein, David LaChappelle, and Amanda LaPore at B Bar.
    - John Knight Opening, 1998 October (Box 14, Folder 44)
      Includes photos from the opening reception of John Knight exhibition at American Fine Arts.
    - AFA X-Mas, 1998 December (Box 14, Folder 45)
      Includes photos of Christmas tree at American Fine Arts made of remnants from John Knight installation, Colin de Land, Esther Friedman, Georg Kargl, and [Dan Asher?]. Also includes photos of artwork by Erik Bulatov: The Royal Family.
    - Crimson and Clover at P.H.A.G., 1999 (Box 14, Folder 46)
      Includes photos of Crimson and Clover, Over and Over, arranged by Colin de Land and performed by Matt McAuley, Josh Diamond, Glynis McDaris, Spencer Sweeney, Brain McPeck, Brian Degraw, and Douglas Anson at Pat Hearn Art Gallery.
    - Armory Show, 2000 February (Box 14, Folder 47)
      Includes photos of booths and visitors at the Armory Show.
    - Colin de Land's Desk, 2002 (Box 14, Folder 48)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land’s desk at American Fine Arts and Margaret Deluccia.
    - Pills, circa 1980s-2003 (Box 14, Folder 49)
      Includes photos of pills in a napkin.
    - Miscellaneous Slides, circa 1980s-2003 (Box 14, Folder 50)
      Includes an assortment of slides, some likely from Zurich or Cologne and include Colin de Land, Jutta Koether, and Esther Friedman. Some slides in this folder are from the early days of American Fine Arts, with Christine Tsvetanov, Mimi Wheeler, Colin de Land, Margaret Deluccia, Erik Oppenheim, and Nina Borgmann.
- Scrapbooks, circa 1980s-2003; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 19
  There are two scrapbooks containing photographs, news clippings, posters, and various pieces of ephemera. Most of the items included in the scrapbooks can be seen hanging on the wall in photographs showing de Land’s desk and the back office space of American Fine Arts. It is likely that these were assembled after de Land’s death. The scrapbooks have been maintained in their original condition.
  - Scrapbook 1, circa 1980s-2003 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook 2, circa 1980s-2003 (Box 19)
- Video and Film Recordings, circa 1980-2003; Series 3; 0.9 Linear feet Box 15, 16, 18
  Audiovisual material is found in two formats: DV mini-cassettes and Super 8 film. Also found is one mini-cassette recording. The majority of the 35 Super 8 films were recorded in Cape Cod, though some show American Fine Arts. Several document the final stages of Pat Hearn’s illness. All but two are silent.
  The videos on the 31 DV mini-cassettes were taken by Colin de Land, primarily in and around the year 2000, using video settings on a digital photographic camera. The content overlaps with the snapshots from this era, many of which are stills from these videos. There is extensive video documenting the end of Pat Hearn’s illness, some coverage of exhibition openings, and a lecture given by Colin de Land.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Material in this series is access restricted. Use requires written permission.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  All audiovisual material in this series has been digitized and is available by special request.
  - Personal Videos, "CD Unlabelled", circa 1999; 5 videocassettes: MiniDV (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Personal Videos, 1999 December 27-2000 August 17; 18 videocassettes: MiniDV (Box 15, Folder 3-7)
  - Personal Videos, 2000 August 15-September 30; 8 videocassettes: MiniDV (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Unidentified Recording, undated; 1 sound cassette (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Home Movies, circa 1980s-2003; 35 film reels: Super 8 mm (Box 18)
- Artifacts, 1988-2008; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 14, 17, 19
  Included here are objects belonging to Colin de Land and Pat Hearn. There is one small painted and matted print by artist Charles Clough, inscribed to Hearn. Also included is a baseball hat frequently worn by de Land and appearing in many of the snapshots and a one page of a calendar signed by model Claudia Schiffer, likely obtained at an autograph event in November 1995. Additionally, there is a copy of the book, Colin de Land: American Fine Arts, edited by Dennis Balk.
  - Artwork, Christmas Gift from Charles Clough, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 51)
    Includes matted 1985 painting Demilunes of Heidenhain inscribed For Pat, Charles Clough, (Christmas 1988).
  - Baseball Hat, 1990s-2003 (Box 17)
  - Signed Claudia Schiffer Calendar Page, 1994 (Box 19)
  - Colin de Land, American Fine Arts Book, 2008 (Box 19)